[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and today
we're talking about something that's very
common in high schools all
across the English speaking world.
That's right today we are
going to talk a little bit about
sexual education or also called sex ed.
So you may be asking yourself what
exactly this means so let's take a
look at this word on vocabulary preview.
Very vocabulary preview. Okay so more
commonly than not we're going to hear the
phrase sex ed ed that stands for education.
This is basically a class or a
training about sexuality and
safety when it comes to these issues.
That's right so as you
said this is a very common
class that is part of the school
curriculum in English speaking countries.
I think maybe students are about 16
to 15 16 years old when they get sex ed.
We had it when I
was about 13 14 13 14.
So it all depends now many countries
don't really have this in their public
schools other countries only have
it in private schools so it's a very
controversial topic about if schools
should actually be teaching this but
we'll talk about that a little bit later
on. Why don't we take a look at today's
dialogue let's listen to
what's happening today.
All right settle down
everyone. As part of this
school's curriculum we'll
be covering sex ed this week.
Now I want everyone to take this
class seriously. Sexual education is very
important and I want you to ask as
many questions as you can think of.
Remember there are
no stupid questions here.
Miss Carlton what exactly is sexual
education? Are you going to teach us
like Kamasutra and stuff like that? No
Jason that's not actually what sex ed is.
Basically we will talk about
sexually transmitted diseases
contraceptives and how the male and
female bodies work. My older sister is in
college and she takes what
she and her friends call the pill.
I never really understood what that is but
I know it has to do with sex or something.
Good point Jason this will be the
topic of our first class contraceptives.
As you mentioned the pill
is one of the many that exist.
The birth control pill is taken daily by
a woman in order to prevent unwanted
pregnancy but it does not
protect her from contracting STDs
from an infected person.
Another popular method is using condoms.
This is probably the best method if
you have sex since it not only prevents
a woman from getting pregnant
but also protects you from STDs.
Yes Jason? What are
condoms made out of?
How is it exactly that a
woman gets pregnant?
Condoms are usually made out
of an elastic material called latex.
As for your other question
that's a whole new class.
All right we're back so now I'm sure
there are a couple of words that we didn't
really understand
there so let's take a look
at a couple of them
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Okay so one of the most
common phrases you're
going to hear when it comes
to sex and safety when you're having
sex is sexually transmitted disease or STD.
That's right so the
teacher actually mentioned
the whole name sexually
transmitted diseases
and also she she used the acronym STDs or
STD in STD and what exactly are these STDs?
Well the key word here is disease these
are illnesses that you can get from sex.
So sexually transmitted
means transmitted or
passed on from one
person to another person
during sex and this
involves this could include
any kind of diseases
like AIDS or syphilis
or chlamydia or gonorrhea
those are the most famous ones.
That's right so sexually
transmitted diseases.
Now why don't we get into
the title of our lesson today,
contraceptives what
are these contraceptives?
Okay so teachers are
always going to explain the
big difference between protection
and contraception or contraceptives.
Basically contraceptives have
to do with getting pregnant.
If you don't want your
girlfriend to get pregnant
in your guy or if you're
a girl and you don't want
to get pregnant you
take contraceptives or you
use contraceptives. There
are many different kinds
and I think the most
common kind for preventing
pregnancy or making
sure you don't get pregnant
is something called the
pill. That's right one of
the kids said that
his sister takes the pill.
Now this is called the pill.
Now you know that pills
are any type of a
capsule or little medicine
that you swallow with
water but what is the pill?
Well this is the birth
control pill so that's
a long name people
often in conversation just
save the pill but it's
called the birth control
pill and it's a pill that
women take every day or
some of them different
times to prevent pregnancy
and so that means that you're
trying not to get pregnant.
That's right okay so this is called a
contraceptive. Now as you mentioned this is a
contraceptive so it will
prevent you from getting
pregnant but it will not
protect you and many of
you may know the most
common form of protection
against pregnancy and
STDs are a little device
called a condom. Okay
so condom is like you said
the most common kind
of protection that people
use and it's important
because it helps you not
only not get pregnant
but also not get a disease
and so people often talk
about this as being the
most important kind of
protection from disease
and pregnancy and
it's basically just a cover
for a man's penis and
it prevents liquids being
passed on from one
person to another person.
That's right and actually
as you mentioned this
has to do with our next
word it prevents you from
contracting STDs like
the teacher mentioned so
to contract an STD or to contract
an illness what does that mean?
Well contract is a special verb
that we use when we're
talking about getting a disease.
You don't say I got
a disease you say I
contracted it that means
I got it from somewhere
or someone and that's
one of the dangers of
sexually transmitted
diseases you can contract
very serious diseases
just by having sex.
Now can I say I
contracted the flu?
I mean it's not incorrect but we
don't really say that with the flu.
It's a very it's not a very serious illness
you say it with very serious diseases.
So yeah I don't think you
would go around saying
I contracted a cold
last week. I got the cold
but and you wouldn't
say this about cancer either
because cancer is not
something you get from
someone else but you say
he contracted AIDS or he
contracted gonorrhea for
example. Okay very good.
So as you see the
spelling is actually the same
as a contract like an
agreement between a company
or two people but the
accident is different a
contract is an agreement
to contract that what we're
talking about illnesses
to get. All right very
good and for our final
word we're going back to
condoms the material
that they are that they are
made out of is called
latex. Okay so latex is a
very special kind of
material that is like they
like they say in the
dialogue elastic it's stretchy
and it's almost plasticky
but it's very very tough
it's very strong and that's why
they make condoms out of it.
And I think we also see things made out
of latex for example doctors when they're
operating they
wear latex gloves.
That's right obviously they don't
want to use materials that are
weak or that are thin
because they need to protect
their patients from
germs and so latex gloves
and latex condoms are
very very common because
they are so so durable.
That's right okay so a
lot of interesting stuff
there why don't we
now jump on over and
take a look at a couple of
different phrases
on fluency builder.
Fluency builder. So this
first phrase is something you
should be very very
familiar with if you've
ever been in a classroom
in America or Canada.
Oftentimes with younger children or
with high school children people get really
worked up very excited
you know kids are yelling
and talking and they're
giggling and they think
that oh sex is so funny
and so the teacher always
says settle down. Settle
down. Okay so if somebody
tells you to settle down hey settle down
settle down that means calm down be quiet.
You're too excited calm down.
So you can use this with your
kids maybe settle down we
need to go come on get in the car.
That's right so just
kind of be quiet be
a little bit calmer it's
very very very important
phrase especially if you're
talking to younger people.
Okay and well of course
when you're talking
about sex with teenagers
or younger people
everyone's laughing and
giggling because it's such a
it's it's such a weird
thing for them and the
teacher said I really want
you to take this class seriously.
Okay so take this
class seriously this
comes from a sentence
structure that's very very
important to take
something seriously.
I take my studies very
seriously or you guys should take
this class seriously
it's important it means
listen pay attention this
is important and you need
to know this it's a
way it's kind of a way to
instruct someone to
really pay attention.
That's right or what if you
say I want you to take me
seriously that means I want
you to really think about
what I'm saying and and
not just talk to me like
a you know like I don't really
understand what's going on.
Okay very good so
to take something
seriously as a structure.
Now moving on to our final
phrase when we were talking
again about contraceptives
we talked about avoiding
pregnancy and we have
a phrase that we use it
called unwanted pregnancy.
Okay so pregnancy is what
happens when someone
gets pregnant they're
going to have a baby but an
unwanted pregnancy is a
certain kind of pregnancy
it means when someone
did not plan to get
pregnant or did not want
to get pregnant so want
unwanted is the opposite
of wanted it means like it
was an accident. Right
so you wouldn't really say
an accidental pregnancy
because it you know it's still a kid.
Exactly so you
didn't want to get
pregnant but you did that's
why we say unwanted pregnancy.
Or you'll hear very often condoms help
prevent unwanted pregnancy or the pill helps
prevent unwanted pregnancy.
That's right okay so a
lot of interesting stuff
there I think it's worthwhile
for us to listen to our
dialogue for one last
time. All right settle
down everyone.
As part of this school's
curriculum we'll be covering
sex ed this week. Now
I want everyone to take
this class seriously
sexual education is very
important and I want you
to ask as many questions
as you can think of.
Remember there are no
stupid questions here.
Miss Carleton what exactly
is sexual education? Are you going to teach
us like Kamasutra and stuff like that?
No Jason that's not
actually what sex ed is.
Basically we will talk about
sexually transmitted diseases,
contraceptives and how the
male and female bodies work.
My older sister is in
college and she takes what
she and her friends
call the pill. I never really
understood what that
is but I know it has to do
with sex or something.
Good point Jason.
This will be the topic of
our first class contraceptives.
As you mentioned the pill
is one of the many that exist.
The birth control
pill is taken daily by
a woman in order to
prevent unwanted pregnancy
but it does not protect
her from contracting
STDs from an infected
person. Another popular
method is using condoms.
This is probably the best
method if you have sex
since it not only prevents
a woman from getting pregnant but
also protects you from STDs. Yes Jason?
What are condoms made
out of? How is it exactly that a
woman gets pregnant?
Condoms are usually made out
of an elastic
material called latex.
As for your other question
that's a whole new class.
All right so coming
back we obviously didn't
cover all forms of
contraception and forms of
protecting yourself
against STDs but I remember
very clearly in school
when we talked about this.
They said the best
protection, the best way to
not get pregnant or
to get STDs is celibacy.
That's right celibacy
is not having any sex.
When I was in school
they said the safest sex is no
sex because there's
always a little bit of
danger and so this is
something that I think they
tell a lot of young people
to scare them but there
is some truth to
it. Yeah of course.
Now what do you think about
this topic? Do you think it's
worthwhile and we
should teach children sexual
education or many people
protest against it and
say this is wrong. We shouldn't be getting
kids condoms when they're in high school.
Personally I think that kids
in most parts of the world will
have sex whether or not
you tell them not to and
so because of that,
because everyone's going to
they're always going
to be people trying it.
I think it's important to
inform students and inform
kids who are in high
school of options and of
safety and of important
health measures because
otherwise you risk unwanted
pregnancies and you
risk people getting these
very serious diseases like AIDS.
That's right I think
it is a very important
topic some countries or
some places even within the
United States are a little
bit more conservative
than others and so many
times they are against
this type of education but
I've actually encountered
people who never
received sexual education
and well until they were maybe like 18 they
thought they can get pregnant by a kiss.
Yeah so I think that's one of
the dangers. Obviously there
are both sides to this
issue and we're curious to
know what you think.
Do you think that sex ed
should be a course or
should be something that
people talk about in schools
in high school or in college?
Do they do this in
your home country?
Let us know. Our website is EnglishPod.com.
All right we'll see you guys there. Bye!